This is exercise five, task three. I'm going
to use XModeler software to solve it. I'm
going to create a project. Let's call it e5t3.
Now we have the project here. Let's create
a diagram. Let's call it anything, just give
it some name. And let's open that diagram.
In this task, we have two class diagrams.
And then we have object diagrams that we are
going to check whether they fit in the class
diagrams. With the xmodeler software, you
don't have to think a lot about whether the
object diagrams, these object diagrams fit
in these class diagrams. All you have to do
is to make the class diagrams correctly in
the software. And then as soon as you try
to make instances, as soon as you try to make
these object diagrams, you will see whether
you are doing something correctly or incorrectly.
So, it's going to warn you, it's going to
show you what you have to do and what the
constraints are basically. We're going to
see this now. Okay, let me do the first class
diagram. So, we have A, B, C and D.
A is a subclass of B. There's an association
between C and D. And it is 1 to 1.
There is an association between A
and C. And it is an aggregation.
There is an association between B
and D, and it is an aggregation.
And just like that we have the first class
diagram. Now, let's go ahead and try these
instances, these object diagrams. The first
one here we have an A and we have a C and
they're connected with some kind of association.
Let's try this here. Now, let's make an A
and a C instance. Okay, no warnings,
nothing happened. So far. So, good. Let's
do B. Sorry, I meant C, let's do an instance
of C.
And now it is giving us a warning. So, let's
make an instance of A. Nothing happened, it
just created the instance, everything's fine.
Let's make an instance of C. And as you can
see here, as soon as we created it, it is
telling us that the saying here, the object
C requires a link to an instance of D at level
zero. So, it is basically enforcing the existence
of an instance of D. Why is this happening?
It is because of this association here. And
we have options, we can actually make the
software ignore this issue for a while.
We can consider the constraints,
we can do it correctly by either creating
a new instance, or choosing an instance that
already exists. So, if you had an instance
of D that already exists somewhere here, we
can choose it and link C to it. Link our instance
of C, I mean. But since we don't have an instance
of D, let's create a new one. Yeah, whatever
call it d1, it's fine. And put it like this.
And now it's saying: “Well, d1 itself now
requires an instance of C.” So, since this
one was created for this C, let's just link
it with it. So, we pick an existing C, which
is this one that we already have. And we press
OK. And now they are linked. And by the way,
let me fix this one. Yes, looks good now.
So, we have our answer now, which is that
this one here, does not fit to this class
diagram here. We don't even have to continue,
we don't even have to make-. Sorry, we don't
even have to make this association. We don't
even need it, we already have a problem, which
is that we have a C that is not linked to
any D while this association is enforcing
the existence of a D for each C. So, here
we have it. xmodeler give us an answer. And
we can continue let's do the rest of the object
diagrams and the other class diagram. Let
me remove this one. Let's try the
other one. We have B, C and D connected to
each other. Let's do this. Not a MetaClass,
should be an instance. So, just like
the previous case, we have this association
here being enforced. And now let's connect
BC and BD. And as you can see, as soon as
we created a link between B and D, these two
instances we have this association now and
it automatically named it as aggr2. So, it
recognizes that we are doing this one here
and now finally, we have a link between B and
C, let's try to do this here. So, link from
B to C and it says there is an error, the
selected objects don't fit any association
definition. And let's look at the object diagram.
This is true, there is no link between something
of class B and something of class C. If this
B that we have here, if it was
a specific type of B, which is some A, a subclass
of B, if it were an instance of A that would
have been fine because of this aggregation,
this association here. But now since it's
just a general B, there is no link between
B and C. And the software is recognizing this
fact. Now let's do the third object diagram,
we have A, B, C, D. And we see that
this one fits, everything is fine. This one
got recognized and is aggr1, this one got
recognized too, this is aggr2, this is the
association that was enforced. Everything's
fine. Now let's do class diagram D, the fourth
class diagram, we have A, C, D. Right
so, this one fits, so everything's fine. Let's
do the last one. We have A, D, D, we have
two D’s. And it is enforcing the
existence of C because of the same association,
this one here. So, we already know that this
one does not fit. Now let's do the second
class diagram. This one here we have A, B,
C, D and we have the same inheritance as the
first one. We have this aggregation, we just
need to change the multiplicity here. We have
this aggregation but instead of going to A,
it's with C and B.
There's a problem here, I meant to edit this
one for some reason it edited this one. Let's
fix it. Let's do the first one.
A and C. So, as soon as we created
an A, it required two D’s. Because and A
is inheriting. An A is a B so it’s inheriting
this aggregation here and this aggregation
enforces the existence of two D’s because
of this multiplicity. So, the answer is it
does not fit. The first one does not fit.
Let's do the second one. We have B C D connected
to each other. And now it is enforcing
the existence of a D. So, we have a D here,
everything's fine. But we're going to need
another D, for this instance of B. And this
does not exist. So, we can already see that
it's not fitting, but let's continue, let's try.
The object B requires a link to an instance
of D at level 0. You tell it, okay, let's
choose the same D here, that D that we already
have. It does not accept. You see it? So,
it wants us to create another D.
And then it says B requires a link to an instance at level 0,
so we choose the d1, this new d. And now it stops complaining.
But now it's already different from what we
have here. Here we have one D. And here we
have two D’s. So, the answer is it does
not fit. Let's do the third one. A,
B, C, D. Again, as soon as we create an A,
it asks us where is the two D’s, it requires
two D’s because just like the first case,
A inherits this aggregation from B. So, the
existence of an A enforces or requires the
existence of two different D’s. So, we already
know this one does not fit. As soon as we
make two D’s here, it's going to look different
from this one. So, the answer is this one
does not fit. Let's continue with this one.
Let's do the fourth one. We have A, C, D.
The same is going to happen. We have an A.
So, we must have two Ds, but here we have
just one and now here the last one. Let's
do the last one. We have A, and the existence of
A requires the existence of two D’s. This
is fine. Let's see if there are any further
problems. And that's it. Nothing
else is being enforced. Nothing is required.
So, this means this one fits.